In the previous issue we've deleted the "feature" branch and then restored it immediately.
We could accomplish it because we knew the commit on which it was pointing previously.
In the real life we usually dont keep track of commits identifiers.
Ref logs will help us to restore the removed branch, even if we forgot the commit id
and to solve other similar situations, that are going to meet us on our dev path in future.
Every time when we switch from one branch to another, make commits,
and, actually in case of any operation that lead to the reference change
git writes the change to a special file that is called "reflog", abbreviation from "reference log".
These files are in the "./git/logs" directory.
For example, reflog for the "HEAD" link is in the ".git/logs/HEAD" file.
And here's what's inside it.
Soon we'll have a look at a special command for having a prettier output of these.
This is just for us to understand how it works.
With every change of the commit to which the HEAD is pointing
which occurs when we update the HEAD itself or when we are moving in a corresponding branch,
new line is added to this file.
It has commits identifiers, where HEAD was pointing previously, where it is pointing now, who when and why made this changes.
For a nicer output of reflogs one usually use the "git reflog" command,
with the link specified, e.g. show the reflog for the master, feature etc.
And, most of the time command is used with no arguements at all, which results in the reflogs for the HEAD.
Thats pretty much the same that we've seen in the file already, but printed in a nicer way and in reverse order.
From the latest changes in the top to older ones in the bottom.
Have a look, please, you see, in the very bottom, the very first line - its the initial commit.
Then we made another commit, and HEAD was pointint to it.
Albeit, strictly speaking, HEAD was not pointing to it directly, but through a branch. But for the reflog it doesnt matter at all.
Then, lets recall the history of our dev process, we made a feature branch.
This fact is not reflected in this log at all. Thats because the HEAD is not being changed by the branch creation itself.
But immediately after that we switched to it, ran the "git checkout" command.
That have updated the HEAD and heres is the entry reflecting it.
Then we made some commits in the feature branch and got back to the master. And so on till the merge of fix and master.
For conciseness, so that the output was not very long,
I've removed some switches of back and forth from the reflog, right before making this video.
But all the main operations have remained.
As you see, our latest actions, namely removing the "fix" and "feature" branches, restoring the "feature"
are not in this log, as they didnt affect the HEAD in any way. Therefore they are not shown here.
Lets note that the addiational information on the references, that you see in the parentheses here, has nothing to do with the reflog
This is so called decoration of the commit identifier, when the information
on the references that are pointing to it now is added to it.
That means if I, for instance, will delete the feature branch now, then feature decoration will be removed from here.
Thats because the information is not stored in the log, it is only shown according to the current state for completeness.
Now, why do we need reflog?
In this issue we are going to see 2 ways of using it.
Forstly, if we, for example, have deleted the "feature" branch a week ago and dont remember what identifiers were there,
but we needed some commits from it, then the usual git log command will not show it to us.
They've become unreachable as there's no feature branch any more.
But as HEAD was pointing to these commits some time ago we can use reflog to find them.
For example we are looking for the "work" function that was developed in this branch. And heres a latest commit on that.
We can also find our way by the last checkout from the branch "feature".
You see, heres when we switched from feature to master for the last time.
In the reflog entries the commit to which we've switched is shown on the right. In our case at that moment its the tip of the "master".
And the commit that we've been at before, the old tip of the "feature" is below.
Lets restore this branch.
To address the reflog notes one can use the braces, same as its here.
i.e. "HEAD" "@" and the number of the entry.
This syntax will get the sixth entry from the reflog and put the corresponding identifier in it.
In windows in powershell "@" is a special symbol, therefore we have to wrap it in a quotes.
But it will work fine in the other shells, just like that. Done, the branch is restored.
Lets note that the "git reflog" command has a number of additional arguements.
You can check them in the documentation.
The normal call assumes "show", as showing reflog is whats needed in 90% of the cases.
But one can delete the entries from the reflog, rewrite the reflogs and check their availability and so on.
So the usual "git reflog" call is the same as "git reflog show" which is an alias of the "git log --oneline -g" command.
Which is,actually turns reflog into a special mode in which it prints the commits from the reflog and not from the branch itself.
You see, the output is exactly same,
as the command is exactly the same as just calling the "git reflog", just longer.
By that many parameters of the "git log" command is applicable to the reflog.
We'll have a look at it in more details in the "git log" command video.
And here we'll just use one of them, namely --date, to add date output to the reflog.
This will make the search in the reflog more convenient, as we approximately remember when the changes we are interested in was made.
As a date format lets take the default iso format.
For more information on the date formats you can watch a date format dedicated issue.
And its easy to see the add time of every entry. Now its easier to find the changes that were done a week ago.
To referr to the entries, I can use date instead of the number in the braces.
Lets say if the feature was deleted, to restore it I can use the as I've done previously "git reflog HEAD@"
Cкажем если удалена feature, то, чтобы ее пересоздать, я могу использовать аналогично предыдущему reflog HEAD@,
but instead of the number (6) as we've done before, I can use the date. In this case this one.
Lets note the space in the date, therefore Im going to put it into quotes, so that git understood it as a whole.
Done.
Here its important to understand that such a call is performed through the reflog, so we are looking for the entries
in the reflog with this date.
If theres noone with this exact date, then the older one that is closest to the one mentioned is used and its commit identifier is taken.
For it to work its not enough for the git commit to be in git.
There should also be an entry in the reflog with the right number or in this case with the matching date.
And we are getting to the next important moment.
By default reflogs are not growing unlimitedly.
Most of the time the entry is stored for 90 days and if commit is unreachable - 30.
So from the moment when we were on the commit we have at least 30 days,
when we can be sure that this entry is in the reflog for sure.
And the commit itself will be in the base.
И сам коммит, соответственно, будет в базе.
The forementioned configuration parameters can be changed, but usually they are left as is.
So, we've just have a look at the reflog usage for restoring the data, namely for finding the lost commits.
This is a very important knowledge not only for the deleted branches,
but for a number of other potentially dangerous operations, that we are going to learn in future.
There is one more way to get to the reflog, that is used in practice very often, usually together with the "git checkout".
It looks like that. So its "@" and a negative number.
This means the previous branch from which we've made the checkout to this one.
So this checkout command is getting us back to the previous branch, from which we've switched to master.
Its fun that in our case its not going to work now.
You see, an error!
When I was recording this screencast I was surprised at first, but then I've figured it out.
Most likely if you think of it you'll figure it out too.
But lets make a small investigation to show what've happened.
How does this command know on which branch were we? Very simple, no black magic involved.
For that it checks the reflog for "HEAD" - checkout is switching the "HEAD" and looks namely for the "checkout" word there.
Lets illustrate this by adding the "--no-decorate" flag that will remove the additional links from the output.
And it looks from the latest checkout from above ... here it is.
And in this line it checks from where the checkout was done. From "fix".
So we need to switch to it, but the "fix" branch was removed, its not there any more, therefore we have the error.
If we put in another negative number git will get back to the specified number of checkouts.
For example if we move back to third checkout it was performed from the "feature".
And as you see, we've switched.
This is of course a very exotic use as -1 is used most of the time.
Now it worked, because we've just made another checkout and currently the previous branch before "feature" was "master".
And we can siwth one again.
Now the previous branch is feature and so on. This calls will siwtch between the master and the feature.
Many git commands know a shorter version of this syntax, just like that "-".
but not all of them. For those that dont we have to write it all.